Wheeling & Lake Erie Railway Company Offices of Vice-President & General Manager Representative Files 5550
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Wheeling & Lake Erie Railway Company Offices of Vice-President & General Manager Representative Files
1931- 1939
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Wheeling &
Lake Erie Railway Company (W&
LE)
United States. National Mediation Board.
5550
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Files of the Vice President and General Manager of the Wheeling and Lake Erie Railway Company consisting of circulars from the National Mediation Board regarding employee representation.
5661774
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, May 11, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, May 11, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Wheeling and Lake Erie Railway Company [WLE] was a railroad that operated primarily in Ohio from 1871 to 1988. The railroad was designed to connect the coal fields around Wheeling, West Virginia with port cities on Lake Erie. In 1948, the WLE was leased to the Nickel Plate Road (New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad). In 1988, the WLE was merged into Norfolk and Western Railway.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1931-1939
Bulk dates: 1934-1938
This collection is comprised of circulars issued by the National Mediation Board [NMB] regarding the representation of railroad employees by labor unions as per the 1934 amendment to the Railway Labor Act [RLA]. The NMB was created by Congress in the 1934 amendment to the RLA; it was the successor agency to the government appointed Board of Mediation which had previously intervened in those disputes between carriers and organized labor that could not be settled by boards of adjustment. One of the main thrusts of the 1934 amendment to the RLA was to ensure that railroad employees were able to join a union voluntarily and without interference from management. This was intended to both protect the workers and to do away with company unions, which disproportionately affected employees in non-operating crafts. The company unions, which were dominated by the company management, limited effective collective bargaining because all the parties were acting in the interests of the company management. The 1934 amendment to the RLA created an election system by which all employees designated in a specific class or craft could cast a ballot for a specific union; the union which gained the support of the majority of those employees was then certified and designated by the NMB as the representative for those employees.
The circulars in this collection, the majority of which are from the 1324 series, are the decisions by the NMB regarding the representation of the employees of various carriers in NMB designated crafts and classes. The circulars are arranged by issue number, with additional decisions, amendments, court proceedings, and other related records to individual certifications filed in reverse chronological order.
This collection also contains NMB circulars 1321 through 1321-3 and individual circulars from other series, as well as a letter to the Wheeling and Lake Erie Railway Company from the NMB alerting the Vice-President of the Railway and the president of the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees to the closing of Case No. A-127.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5806: U.S. National Mediation Board Agreements
United States. National Mediation Board.; Railroads -- United States.; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States.; Collective bargaining -- Railroads -- United States.; United States. Railway Labor Act.; Wheeling and Lake Erie Railway Company
5661774
- Employee Representation. All Employees. NMB Circulars 1324 to 1324-10, 1934-1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Employee Representation. All Employees. NMB Circulars 1324-11 to 1324-33, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Employee Representation. All Employees. NMB Circulars 1324-34 to 1324-65, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Employee Representation. All Employees. NMB Circulars 1324-66 to 1324-76, 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Employee Representation. All Employees. NMB Circulars 1324-78 to 1324-97, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Scope and Contents
  Missing NMB Circulars 1324-77; 1324-78(e); 1324-81; 1324-89
- Employee Representation. All Employees. NMB Circulars 1324-99 to 1324-128, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Missing NMB Circulars 1324-98; 1324-117; 1324-125
- Employee Representation. All Employees. NMB Circulars 1324-129 to 1324-164, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Missing NMB Circular 1324- 140
- Employee Representation. All Employees. NMB Circulars 1324-165 to 1324-220, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Missing NMB Circulars 1324-166; 1324-167; 1324-183; 1324-190 to 1324-200; 1324-202 to 1324-205; 1324-209 to 1324-217.
- Employee Representation. All Employees. NMB Circulars 1324-221 to 1324-254, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Missing NMB Circulars 1324-222 to 1324-226; 1324-229 to 1324-231; 1324-235.
- Employee Representation. All Employees. NMB Circulars 1324-255 to 1324-280, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Missing NMB Circulars 1324-257; 1324-626; 1324-266; 1324- 267; 1324-271.
- Employee Representation. All Employees. NMB Circulars 1321 to 1321-3, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Letter from National Mediation Board to W&LE Railway Company re Case No. A-127, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Employee Representation, General File, 1931-1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)